Collaboration Meeting with Emory - January 10, 2011

Format: telcon

Date: Mon 10th Jan 2011

Time: 15:00 - 16:00 (BST) / 10:00 - 11:00 (EST)

Attendance

Emory - Stephen Wheat, Tod Jackson

Manchester - Carole Goble, Steve Petiffer, Shoaib Sufi, Jiten Bhagat, Mannie Tagagira

EBI - None

Minutes

Carole brought up two main areas of discussion:

The software - contribution protocol, common roadmap, common development, etc.

The BioCatalogue service and content

We discussed the points individually…

1. Software

Bring together collaboration on the various components that comprise the BioCatalogue software, as well as the external apps being built by both sides (Mass Curator app, iPhone and iPad apps, and so on).

The focus of PESC work was particularly on customisation configuration machinary and security/sharing permissions

We discussed the need for a CLA and governance model to get us started, with the longer term aim to have the Emory folks on board as first class project members.

Stephen mentioned that they are very familiar with CLAs and working as contributors and are happy for us to start off with a CLA and goverance model they can look over

ACTION: Shoaib to send Stephen a CLA and governance model based on the Taverna ones.

Tod mentioned that collaboration on the roadmap is the first and key thing we need to do. Very important! Need to align common goals and requirements and figure out where to make things more extensible/configurable for niche needs.

Stephen: Tod's point is important in the context of the existing deployments and continual running of these instances (e.g.: the internal BioCat instance they are running for EdUnify).

Stephen and Tod both emphasised that one (of many) points is that of a “virtual private registry” - people are worried about the perceived security and visibility of their services. Some communities want to be able to hide services as they are developing and annotating them, and then incrementally reveal them. And even then, some only want to reveal to certain groups and sub-sets of people.

Security objects from biomedical community CIOs - non-sensible vs sensible (mistaking the information about the service with the running of the service and information about the service giving outsiders a potential advantage)

Jits suggested that we get Tod involved with the current 2011 roadmapping work asap. First figure out the developer roadmap and then distil a user facing roadmap from that.

ACTION: Jits to add Tod to internal developer list and wiki and then point him to 2011 roadmap WIP page.

ACTION: Jits to arrange a roadmapping meeting with Tod (and who else?)

2. Existing content + services

This was about providing curation help for the existing BioCat service and improving it's content.

Discussion brought about methods to improve on curation, using things such as:

- User leaderboards and mini games (using points systems like how stackoverflow.com and others do). - Service annotation levels (to visually depict how well services are annotated). - More focus on example data. - Ability to run services directly in the catalogue, to be able to figure how they work, and to be able to generate example data.

These are examples of things to discuss in the roadmapping meeting.

Any Other Business

Stephen: education, research and health sciences are all interested. They have lots of services! The biohealth/biomedical folks may be able to help curation of the BioCatalogue.org service.

ACTION: Stephen to speak with the Research Health Sciences group with a view to assisting the curation of the public BioCatalogue

ACTION: Stephen to invite Manchester to give seminars to various groups (RHS, Joel's group)

Any other business:

Stephen mentioned conference opportunities.

The conferences mentioned to submit jointly to are:

ISMB/ECCB

HCISC

Educause

SOA/Java

IEEE ICWS

(and we could also try DCC)

Journals could include Nature BioTech

We also discussed that PESC may need to develop a business plan and charge fees.

ACTION: Stephen will contact us if this occurs for our views

ACTION: Carole to formally get the agreement of the EBI for opening up the complete mailing lists to Emory

Actions

Shoaib to send Stephen a CLA and governance model based on the Taverna ones.

Jits to add Tod to internal developer list and wiki and then point him to 2011 roadmap WIP page.

Jits to arrange a roadmapping meeting with Tod (and anyone else interested).

Stephen to speak with the Research Health Sciences group with a view to assisting the curation of the public BioCatalogue.

Stephen to invite Manchester to give seminars to various groups (RHS, Joel's group).

Stephen will contact us if/when PESC have a business plan for their installation.

Carole to formally get the agreement of the EBI for opening up the complete mailing lists to Emory.

The BioCatalogue Roadmap

Please note that the time scales listed are estimated. New requirements and changes in the user community may affect the delivery dates and schedule.

First quarter of 2009 (Jan - Mar)

Private pilot (private beta) - Basic SOAP services registration, discovery and annotation. Batch upload of soaplab services.

Better service discovery and filtering - Search result sorting and filtering (by providers and services types) and more faceted browsing features. At a glance counts of annotations on services.

Service annotation support - Simple tagging and functional description of services, operations, their inputs and outputs. Support for service operation inputs and outputs examples. Support for comments and discussion threads about services. Annotation provided by submitters, providers, expert curators and automated agents.

REST services support - Ability to register, describe and search for REST services in BioCatalogue.

Content acquisition (I) - Import Feta annotation. Providers, experts and users' service registration and annotation.

Second quarter of 2009 (Apr - Jun)

Public pilot (public beta) - First public release - see The Pilot

Service monitoring - availability - We will regularly monitor the service, by checking the host, endpoints, WSDL and so on.

Service monitoring - testing - Test scripts to test out service functionality can be provided by submitters and service providers. We then run these regularly to provide us with metrics on the availability/reliability. A traffic light system (red, green, amber) gives users an at-a-glance view on status.

Semantic annotation support - Ability to annotate service using ontologies (and possibly export semantically annotated services in different formats such as SAWSDL, SA-REST).

Enhanced search functionality - Similarity searches. Semantic search: search for services using terms from a defined ontology. Amazon-like search: people who searched for these also searched for those.

Public APIs (I) - Basic RESTful APIs to BioCatalogue (mainly read).

Integration with myExperiment - Services from BioCatalogue displayed in myExperiment so users of myExperiment can browse them.

Content acquisition (II) - Merge with the EMBRACE registry. Scavenge services from SeekDa and ProgrammableWeb.

BioMoby services support - Ability to register and search for BioMoby services.

Third quarter 2009 (Jul - Sep)

Subscribe to a service - RSS/ATOM feeds for services, providing information on all activity on a service within BioCatalogue.

Notifications and new feeds - RSS/ATOM feeds and email notifications to keep users informed of new and updated services in BioCatalogue.

Advanced service discovery and filtering - Filtering by multiple tags, providers, service types, locations, and so on.

Fourth quarter 2009 (Oct - Dec)

Public APIs (II) - More functional RESTful APIs to BioCatalogue (read and write).

Service usage metrics - Usage metrics collection and provider metrics submission. RSS/ATOM feeds and email notifications for these metrics.

“Try it now” service functionality - Ability to test and play with a service within the BioCatalogue interface before using it.

Integration with Taverna - Ability to import Web Services and annotations to and from BioCatalogue and Taverna.

2010

myBioCatalogue - Ability to set up your own local BioCatalogue registry.

Curation workbench/tools - New curation tools designed for expert curators.

Date: Tuesday 11th Nov 2008

Time: 15:00-17:00 (UK)

Attending

Manchester: Jiten, Franck, Constantinos

EBI: Thomas, Eric

Apologies

Carole, Rodrigo, Hamish, Katy

Minuting

Eric

Agenda

Action from the last telcon.

Progress with the pilot - are we rolling?

BioCatalogue public wiki

Next BioCatalogue F2F

support for SAWSDL/WSMO/SA-REST

AOB.

Actions from Previous Meeting

Eric: read EBI privacy policy and make sure we have a version appropriate for BioCatalogue - incorporate commments from Sergejs (and others, if any).

Jits and Franck: add content to the Biocatalogue wiki

Franck: mail the friends list with features for the pilot and when it will be available, along with a roadmap for after the pilot.

Jits: Ask Carole what is happening on the 27th November - is there a Biocatalogue meeting in Edinburgh to meet up with Mark W

Minutes

The urgency to release the pilot BioCatalogue was the main issue for discussion. The developers indicated that they were doing all they could to get the pilot released as soon as possible. Unfortunately, there were a few problems with the deployment which they were putting every effort into solving. The expectation was that the pilot will be release before the end of the week for internal use, and and beginning of next week to BioCatalogue friends.

New Actions

Action Thomas : link the public wiki from the main biocatalogue.org site

Action Eric : read through wiki content and send comments to Frank/Jiten

Action Eric and Thomas : join the meeting with Steve from Embrace on Wednesday, Nov 19th

Action Eric, Jiten, Thomas : Release the internal pilot with release notes

Action Jiten, Franck : Prioritize the roadmap items and add time estimates

Action Franck : email the list of possible dates for the project F2F so that people can indicate their availability

Action Franck : Provide an example of a semantically annotated service(using the SAWSDL model)

Action Everyone : Read the SA-REST proposal and comment on how we can participate

Upcoming Meetings

Semantic Web Applications and Tools for Life Sciences - 28/11/08 http://www.swat4ls.org/

Syngenta 12 November - Franck to describe and possibly demo Biocatalogue. If the pilot is not ready, he will show screenshots

AOB

Previous/Next Meetings

Previous meeting:Phone Conference Meeting on Nov 04 2008

Next meeting:Phone Conference Meeting on Nov 18 2008

Date: Tuesday 03rd Feb 2009

Time: 15:00-16:00 (UK)

Telcon No: 08445805588

Pin: 70503010

Attending

Manchester: Franck, Jits

EBI: Eric, Thomas

Apologies

Rodrigo, Carole, Steve

Agenda

Actions from the last telcon

Progress with the pilot

Test infrastructure setup at EBI

Review of January tasks

Next steps following release to friends list

Code releases(tags)

Progress of 20 Questions (to clarify user requirements)

AOB - meeting date to be moved ???

Actions from Previous Meeting

Franck : Provide an example of a semantically annotated service(using the SAWSDL model). completed

Jits/Thomas/Eric: create developer section on the wiki. ongoing

Franck: make an announcement about latest changes to schedule to the friends list. completed

Action all : update the 20 questions section on the wiki ongoing

Action Jits/Eric : Investigate how to add some form of classification of the services. will use tag instead…action completed

Action Franck : Put up a service classification draft on the wiki. cancel

Minutes

From now on we should announce on the friend list anytime we add new features or do update of the beta site. Also anything happening within the project should be announced on the friend list.

we need to discuss with Rodrigo the test infrastructure setup at EBI. should we re-use EMBRACE infrastructures?

New Actions

Franck: start an FAQ on the wiki

Upcoming Meetings

Meeting with Francois from INRA about service monitoring 12/02/09

AOB

There will be a demo at the Strategic Advisory Board Meeting in February

There is potential for collaboration with Microsoft. Initial discussions on-going with Carole

Previous/Next Meetings

Previous meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Jan 27 2009

Next meeting:

Host Servers(Live & Test)

  Operating System : CentOS release 5.5 (Final) x86_64\\
  Virtual Machine     : KVM\\
  Virtual CPU            : 1\\
  RAM                        : 2 GB  (can be easily increased)\\
  Local Disk              : 20 GB\\
  File system             : NFS (has access to TB sized file system) \\

Search Server

On each of the servers there is also a Tomcat running localhost:8080 which hosts the solr application. The solr application is used for the search and apart form reading there are also writes happen. This means only one Tomcat server on the live machines can be active at a time. This is done through the Zeus load balancer by configuring an active/passive setup.

  Tomcat 6.0.26\\
  Java 1.6.0_20\\
  Solr 1.3.0\\

  test instance -Xms256m -Xmx512m\\
  prod istance -Xms1024m -Xmx1024m\\

Ruby

We use the Ruby Enterprise Edition as the Ruby runtime. It is installed on NFS under /nfs/public/rw/webadmin/ruby.

  Ruby (ruby-enterprise-1.8.7-2010.02 ) 1.8.7\\

live:
ruby -v
ruby 1.8.7 (2010-04-19 patchlevel 253) [x86_64-linux], MBARI 0×6770, Ruby Enterprise Edition 2010.02
gem -v
1.3.7

test:
ruby -v
ruby 1.8.7 (2010-04-19 patchlevel 253) [x86_64-linux], MBARI 0×6770, Ruby Enterprise Edition 2010.02
gem -v
1.3.7

Memcache

We are using the memcahed provided by the EPEL repository.

  Memached 1.4.5\\
  PORT 11211\\
  CACHESIZE 256MB\\

Apache

There are different ways to host Ruby on Rails application but we choose to use mod_rails which is an Apache module. The Apache is the standard installation provided by Centos 5.5.

  Apache 2.2.3 \\
  passenger 2.2.15 (mod_rails)\\

MySQL

The MySQL database are managed by the DBA team (dba@ebi.ac.uk) in the systems group. There are tow MySQL instances:

  live (host = mysql-biocat-prod.ebi.ac.uk port = 4152) \\
  test (host = mysql-biocat-dev.ebi.ac.uk port = 4151)\\

Both versions are running MySQL Community Server 5.0.41 .
Test Harness Server

The test server is running untrusted scripts so we create a one off Linux machine running Fedora 14. fedora was chosen since it offers a lot more and newer
packages for dynamic languages. The box has no NFS mounted and is kept as isolate as possible. Still this part of the infrastructure is risk for the general security.
Firewall and Proxy Configuration

The Virtual machines are protected through a firewall which is managed by systems. Systems also provides proxy server (http://www-proxy.ebi.ac.uk:3128)
which must be used by applications if the want to connect to remote hosts with http(s). This restrictions are in place to stop intruders to reload code
from remote hosts if the manage to compromise a web application. This settings also mean that one cannot use any other TCP based protocols (git, twitter, etc)
apart form http(s).

Date: Tuesday 09th Dec 2008

Time: 15:00-17:00 (UK)

This was a skype chat instead of a telcon

Attending

Manchester: Jits, Franck

EBI: Eric

Apologies

Thomas, Carole, Katy, Hamish, Rodrigo

Minuting

Jits

Agenda

Actions from the last telcon

Progress with the pilot

New requirements timeline and planning

Updating the BioCatalogue public wiki

AOB

Actions from Previous Meeting

Action Eric, Jiten, Thomas : Release the internal pilot with release notes. Cancelled

Action Franck : Provide an example of a semantically annotated service(using the SAWSDL model). Ongoing

Jits: add number of service in the catalogue to the index page. Done

Jits: add Franck to support list. Done

Thomas: investigate 'home' link on the public wiki. Ongoing

Jits/Thomas/Eric: create developer section on the wiki. Ongoing

Minutes

Progress with the pilot

Jits: merged annotations work into trunk. This includes some UI work so now tags and descriptions can be added, and will be shown. Next thing is to have tags and descriptions for operations. Also, comments. Also working on annotations plugin documentation.

Eric: wrapping all of service submission into one transaction. Also, OpenSearch description doc implemented.

Franck: what about bulk submission of services? - we have that functionality in the codebase but needs to be enabled and tested properly first, if prioritised.

New requirements timeline and planning

Revised requirements list and planning document started last Friday (day after F2F meeting).

Jits: suggest we plan for rest of Dec and early Jan, for now. Then early Jan we do a planning activity to flesh out the rest.

Updating the BioCatalogue public wiki

Franck will update the roadmap and rest of wiki, but do we need to something about the website at this stage? Fine for now.

New Actions

Eric: list the features of the current pilot (including annotations stuff), so that they can be used in a email announcing the private beta to the friends list.

Franck: read through the revised requirements and planning doc and update the private wiki roadmap accordingly. Then after approval copy it to the public wiki.

Franck: make an announcement about latest changes to schedule to the friends list.

Thomas: possibly change the “Wiki” link on the main website and beta site to something more descriptive like “More info about the project”. Also add this to the “About us” page.

Upcoming Meetings

AOB

Previous/Next Meetings

Previous meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Nov 25 2008

Next meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Dec 16 2008

Next Steps for Service Monitoring

How does monitoring work at the moment?

There are two ways monitoring is done:

By running simple checks on URL (endpoints and wsdl locations)

By executing test scripts (on a separate server)

To a large extent this all works well especially with the non-endpoint URL checks. However, the issues which were raised at the beginning especially with maintainability of the test script approach are still there. Now that the system is in place, it is probably a good time to examine what could be improved.

The two main issues with the current system are :

maintainability of the test script mechanism in the long term, especially if there is no full time effort for the BioCalogue at EBI

The correctness of the implementation of the endpoint checks( for REST and SOAP services )

At the moment, this is implemented for soap services by sending an empty soap message to the endpoint which in many cases would respond with a soap fault. However, there is no consistency in the format of the responses sent meaning that there is no certainty in the case of a failure. Given this situation, it is either necessary to customize monitoring for failing endpoints or to try a different approach.

Using Nagios for URL checks

[[http://www.nagios.org|Nagios) is a purpose built system for monitoring network infrastructure. Nagios will be able to give us monitoring, reporting and alerts. Also, as an industry standard tool, there is already a community around it with the possibility that tooling for our future monitoring needs may already exist. Additionally, at EBI, nagios is already being used for monitoring all sorts of network infrastructure. This will be one way of getting some sustainability effort for BioCatalogue through the system administrators who already maintain the nagios system.

Use current test scripts only as examples. Not executed

The current test script mechanism would serve as a way to let users submit sample clients which other users could download and execute in their own environments. The BioCatalogue should not have to execute these. These will shield the BioCatalogue from potential issues of keeping the script library versions in sync with developer environments. Users can therefore provide scripts independent of the BioCatalogue's capability of executing them.

Promote the soapUI mechanism as the way to do functional testing with BioCatalogue

It seems that many developers of services in BioCatalogue are already using soapUI for their development. I have not done any survey on this so this is just anecdotal from talking to people. The advantage of using this soapUI approach is that it actually serves both as an availability and functional test. This especially the endpoint availability which is not handled completely by the current endpoint checking mechanism. Also given that all the user needs is to submit is an xml file, it is cleaner and safer.

Note Having examined the current test scripts in BioCatalogue, it seems that most are doing very trivial functional testing anyway. The INB tests for example, just construct a URL which they call and then parse the expected trivial XML. Soaplab test scripts are generated via builder script. According to Mahmut, he could generate soapUI project files in more less the same manner. While these are not the most pressing issues on the catalogue, it will be good to have them in perpective.

The BioCatalogue REST API - Use Cases

Various use cases have been taken into account in order to build an API that provides a balance between utility and simplicity.

This includes scenarios ranging from building simple scripts and mashups to integration with scientific workflow workbenches (like Taverna) and other repositories/registries.

Three projects have helped drive the main use cases and requirements so far:

An alpha version BioCatalogue plugin for Taverna has been released. See the Taverna plugins page for more info. This integrates data and functionality from BioCatalogue in order to aid in the workflow design and execution process.

The ONIX Portal developed by the NCRI.

Integration into the myExperiment workflows repository environment.

Following is a list of various use cases and requirements considered:

Search the registry for services and other things, using simple keyword queries.

Filter the services from the registry based on some criteria.

Get all the important data about a service (service details, operations along with inputs/outputs and data formats, most important annotations, such as tags, descriptions, etc).

Get a summarised view of a service (that includes general information about the service) that allows easy harvesting of content from the BioCatalogue.

Get current monitoring status of a service.

Get monitoring history of a service.

Build a tag cloud of the most popular tags.

Find information about a specific SOAP operation that is used in a workflow. Such as example data, data formats, descriptions, etc.

Search the registry by tags (regular free text tags / those coming from an ontology).

Search for a service by its WSDL location.

Get all available annotations about a service.